Adam, Meldrum & Anderson Company Historical Files
Buffalo History Museum. Research Library
Adam, Meldrum & Anderson Company Historical Files
1867 - 1984
5 boxes + 1 scrapbook (3.0 linear ft.)
Adam, Meldrum & Anderson Company (Buffalo, N.Y.)
The Buffalo History Museum 1 Museum Court Buffalo, NY 14216 Phone: 716-873-9644 ext. 306 Fax: 716-873-8754 Email: library@buffalohistory.org URI: http://www.buffalohistory.org
Arranged and described by Patricia Virgil, May 14, 1996.
Adam, Robert, 1833-1904; Adam, R. B. (Robert Borthwick), 1863-1940; Adam, Robert B., III (Robert Borthwick), 1918-1993; Department stores New York (State) Buffalo.; original photographs; scrapbooks; sheet music
Researchers wishing to access this collection must apply for a Scholar Pass and present valid photo ID upon arrival to the library.
Buffalo department store founded in 1867. Robert B. Adam (1833-1904) came to the United States from Scotland in 1857. He worked for the Boston firm of Hogg, Brown and Taylor for ten years and, in 1867, moved to Buffalo. With partners Herbert A. Meldrum and Alexander Whiting, he opened a store on Main St. where the American Hotel had stood. Alexander Whiting retired in 1872. In 1876, William Anderson was admitted to the partnership, and the name of the firm was changed to Adam, Meldrum & Anderson. Robert B. Adam’s younger brother, J.N. Adam, also came to Buffalo from Scotland. He opened his own store across the street from Adam, Meldrum & Anderson. Robert B. Adam II (1863-1940) assumed the presidency of the store upon his father’s death in 1904. Robert B. Adam III became president in 1945. He supervised both the opening of the first AM&A’s branch store at University Plaza in 1947, and the move of the downtown store across Main St. to the former J.N. Adam building in 1960. Adam, Meidrum & Anderson was sold to The Bon Ton Stores in 1994. The downtown store was closed in 1995.
This collection was assembled in anticipation of the store’s 100th anniversary in 1967. It consists mainly of promotional materials, including newspaper inserts, merchandise catalogs, and advertisements. There are also several books and some sheet music published by the store; clippings, 1867-1981; a scrapbook documenting the downtown move, 1960; and some photographs of AM&A’s stores and employees.
Collection is arranged into 10 series:
I. Correspondence, 1918-1984
II. Store receipts, 1883-1941
III. Advertising, sales and promotion, 1897-1967
IV. Books published by Adam, Meldrum & Anderson, ca. 1895-1932
V. Company history, 1960-1967
VI. Employees, 1930-1983
VII. Agreements, plans and miscellaneous, 1909-1918, and undated
VIII. Clippings, 1867-1981
IX. Sheet music, 1879-1909
X. Photographs
- I. Correspondence, 1918-1984 (Box-folder 1.1)
  - Folder 1: Correspondence, 1834-1984
- II. Store receipts, 1883-1941 (Box-folder 1.2)
  - Folder 2: Store receipts, 1883-1941
- III. Advertising, sales and promotion, 1897-1967 (Box-folder 1.3-14. 2.1-8)
  - Folder 3: Form letters to customers, 1918-1960
  - Folder 4: Newspaper advertising campaign, 1931
  - Folder 5: Newspaper advertising campaign, 1932
  - Folder 6: Newspaper advertising campaign, 1933-1936
  - Folder 7: Newspaper advertising campaign, undated
  - Folder 8: Half-price sale newspaper inserts, 1933-1935
  - Folder 9: Half-price sale newspaper inserts, 1939-1940
  - Folder 11: Christmas gift guide newspaper insert, 1940
  - Folder 12: Anniversary sale newspaper inserts, 1933-1936
  - Folder 13: Anniversary sale newspaper inserts, 1937-1938
  - Folder 14: Anniversary sale newspaper inserts, 1939-1940
  - Folder 1: Sales comparison and radio promotions, 1939, n.d., 1936
  - Folder 2: Advertising cards, folders and slingers, ca. 1900-1919
  - Folder 3: Advertising cards, folders and slingers, ca. 1920-1956
  - Folder 4: other advertising, ca. 1897-1972
  - Folder 5: Catalogs and other promotional publications, ca. 1900-1967
  - Folder 6: Christmas gift catalog, 1964
  - Folder 7: Fashion show invitations, tickets and programs, 1947-1956
  - Folder 8: Paper shopping bags
- IV. Books published by Adam, Meldrum & Anderson, ca. 1895-1932 (Box-folder 2.9-10)
  - Folder 9: Economy cookbook, 1883
  - Folder 10: Children's book, Buffalo views, Buffalo centennial souvenir, ca. 1895-1932
- V. Company history, 1960-1967 (Box-folder 3.1-3)
  - Folder 1: AM&A histories, 1967
  - Folder 2: AM&A Day album, Aug. 1, 1960, August 1, 1960
  - Folder 3: Scrapbook re downtown move, 1959-1960 (wrapped separately)
- VI. Employees, 1930-1983 (Box-folder 3.4)
  - Folder 4: Programs for outings, notices from management, etc.
- VII. Agreements, plans and miscellaneous, 1909-1918, and undated (Box-folder 3.5)
  - Folder 5: Partnership agreement, department floor plans, and other items, 1909-1918, and undated
- VII. Clippings, 1867-1981 (Box-folder 3.6-14, 4.1-7)
  - Folder 6: Clippings, 1867-1897
  - Folder 7: Clippings, 1901-1918
  - Folder 8: Clippings, 1921-1929
  - Folder 9: Clippings, 1930-1932
  - Folder 10: Clippings, 1933
  - Folder 11: Clippings, 1934-1935
  - Folder 12: Clippings, 1936
  - Folder 13: Clippings, 1937
  - Folder 14: Clippings, 1938-1939, [1930s]
  - Folder 1: Clippings, 1940-1949
  - Folder 2: Clippings, 1950-1959
  - Folder 3: Clippings, 1960
  - Folder 4: Clippings, 1961-1966
  - Folder 5: Clippings, 1967-1969
  - Folder 6: Clippings, 1970-1981
  - Folder 7: Clippings, n.d.
- IX. Sheet music, 1879-1909
  - Folder 1: Sheet music, published by AM&A, 1879-1909
- X. Photographs (Box-folder 5.2-9)
  - Folder 2: Adam family
  - Folder 3: Board of directors and employees
  - Folder 4: Store exteriors and interiors
  - Folder 5: Downtown move/opening day, 1960
  - Folder 6: Events
  - Folder 7: Generator, float, misc.
  - Folder 8: Oversize (Adam family, board, employees, downtown move, branch stores)
  - Folder 9: J. Keith Alford, Robert B. Adam (stored in icon)